<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>GETRF</title><link href="http://hipercom.inria.fr/Project-GETRF/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://hipercom.inria.fr/Project-GETRF/feeds/overview.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://hipercom.inria.fr/Project-GETRF/</id><updated>2014-10-13T16:10:44+02:00</updated><entry><title></title><link href="http://hipercom.inria.fr/Project-GETRF/.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-13T16:10:44+02:00</updated><author><name>Ichrak Amdouni</name></author><id>tag:hipercom.inria.fr/Project-GETRF,2014-10-13:.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Context of the project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.agence-nationale-recherche.fr"&gt;
The French National Research Agency&lt;/a&gt; launches 
in partnership with the Defense Procurement Agency (DGA) a programme called 
&lt;a href="http://www.agence-nationale-recherche.fr/en/research-programmes/aap-en/
specific-support-for-research-works-and-innovation-defense-astrid-2011/nc/"&gt;ASTRID&lt;/a&gt;: 
Specific support for research works and innovation defense. 
This programme is funded entirely by the DGA and is housed at the ANR 
which ensures its implementation.
ASTRID is a programme dedicated to support small research projects 
with a highly exploratory and innovative nature, with a duration of 
less than 36 months and whose applications are dual (both civilian and military). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scope of the Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GETRF project focuses on &lt;b&gt;wireless multihop military networks&lt;/b&gt;. The aim is to propose new mechanisms
to improve the performance of these networks. &lt;br&gt; 
This project considers wireless multihop networks as a whole of which &lt;b&gt;mobile ad hoc networks 
(MANETs) and sensor wireless networks (WSNs)&lt;/b&gt; are specific cases, 
with both differences and commonalities. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br clear="all"&gt; 
The goal is to address two major challenges in tactical military networks: 
&lt;ul class="list2 pad_bot2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt; Efficient management of energy, latency and network capacity.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt; Efficient management of the network in mobile or degraded environment.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These objectives may for instance answer two scenario of functioning of military tactical networks:
&lt;ul class="list2 pad_bot2"&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt; A stabilized and static situation in operating normally&lt;/b&gt;, where the goal is to optimize the 
    network usage.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt; The case of more critical scenarios&lt;/b&gt;, for instance, 
    the case of high mobility, the case of unexpected degradation of the quality 
    of one part of the network, and, also, the case where the broadcast information is exceeding the capacity, which are all cases where
    the goal is to operate despite the very high constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Research directions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer these objectives, GETRF targets a layered architecture combining three type of mechanisms: 
&lt;ul class="list2 pad_bot2"&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;b&gt;Network coding techniques&lt;/b&gt;. These recent schemes allow for more robust information
     broadcast in the case of changes in the network (mobility, degradation of one part of the network), 
     to reduce the control traffic exchanges, and more generally, to increase network efficiency
      (less transmissions, more capacity). 
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;b&gt;Node coloring techniques&lt;/b&gt;. They allow time-slots to be assigned to nodes or links of the wireless network. 
    These techniques allow one to build efficient Time Division Multiple Access techniques. The medium access 
    scheme obtained can be very energy efficient (low duty cycle) and can also offer very good end-to-end delays. 
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;b&gt;Opportunistic routing schemes&lt;/b&gt;. Opportunistic routing protocols, usually based on 
    geographic routing, can improve the total throughput of ad hoc networks. They can also be combined with medium access schemes 
    to build network nodes operating in low-duty cycle mode. These schemes 
    can be very energy efficient. Another application of opportunistic routing is a coupling with mobility 
    (mobile opportunistic routing schemes). On can take advantage of nodes' mobility to optimize the delivery delay. 
&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Perspectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For wireless sensor networks, GETRF paves the way for very energy efficient networks while offering acceptable data delivery delays. 
For surveillance applications (therefore carrying very little information), the project should lead to networks with very long lifetimes.
For ad hoc networks, the GETRF project aims at supporting networks with high mobility where the current networks based on protocols such as OLSR or
AODV cannot be used with extreme mobility.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>